[Music]
hello everybody good evening and good
day to all of you welcome to the 47th
live episode of ask abhijit
i hope you are all doing well let us see
who all is there with us tonight
or today wherever you are i can see
rohan gupta karthik tanda yeshwanth
kingster gaming tuntu
kiran raj
anketh
sahil
shah john price aryan khanna
and so many more people good evening
good day to all of you it is so nice to
be back with you all
live on a new episode
so today it's a live episode i have not
pre-selected any questions i'm going to
take your questions live from the chat
so go ahead ask me questions what shall
we talk about today
you decide what we talk about today do
we talk about history
geopolitics physics science
astrophysics aliens philosophy
spirituality
decide you guys decide all right please
ask me some questions and i shall answer
your questions
so let's see what questions we have
okay aryan says aryan asks about the
mistakes done by the great shri
jawaharlal nehru the selected prime
minister of india
well i think people have written entire
books about the mistakes that sri
jawaharlal nehru has made
i mean you can have several phd thesis
on this particular topic you can write
numerous books
on the mistakes that mr nero did i can
list a few
from the very beginning he allowed
the pakistanis to take over a
significant portion of kashmir and jammu
and kashmir and ladakh i mean if he had
waited for two or three days the indian
army would have taken back all our all
our territory but he prevented them from
doing it and he said we will go to the
u.n and we'll resolve it amicably which
has never happened we are still
we are still not in a situation where
this this issue is resolved and
and the fact is that it was indian
territory
why do you need to go to the un to a
third party to resolve the issue
use your own armed forces but he he
refused to do that and that's why
we have this problem then you have the
indus waters treaty the most unequal
treaty in human history most likely
i mean treaties are done between two
equal powers india is an enormously
larger power than pakistan and yet in
the treaty
more than 80 percent of the waters of
the in this
region
they are allocated to pakistan
why such an unequal treaty treaty why
then he gave away the cocoa islands to
burma as a gift as if it was his own
property he gave away money
valet to burma again as a gift as if it
was his ancestry property
he refused the sultan of oman's offer
to give india the port of gwadar for
free without any price he refused that i
don't want that he said who the hell was
he to decide he did not want that
then he prevented nepal from rejoining
india the king of nepal
wanted to rejoin india he requested mr
nairo he requested the indian government
to allow nepal to rejoin india mr nero
said no i will not allow that
then there were two offers
to india for a permanent membership of
the un security council
there were two offers in 1950 and 1955
the first offer was in 1950 the second
offer was in 1955 both the most powerful
countries of the world the us and the
ussr were together in this they both
wanted india
to become a permanent member of the u.n
security council with veto power
mr nero said no i will not i do not want
this it has to it should be given to
china first first give it to china then
we will think about india that's what he
said
and these are just some a few examples
of the article 3 370 in kashmir that was
again his handiwork mr nehru
and so much more he allowed tibet
to be taken over by china
india had a significant presence in
tibet at the time tibet was essentially
a protectorate of the british raj and
that mantle passed on to india after
india's
the transfer of power to the indian
government in 1947
so india could have protected tibet
india could have prevented china from
invading an annexing tibet
and instead of preventing that mr nehru
ensured that the chinese pla people's
enslavement army or people's liberty
liberation army he ensured that indian
rice was supplied to these invading
soldiers
and
had this indian rice not been supplied
to the chinese invaders they would never
have been able to
take over tibet
so nehru actively participated in
china's
invasion and annexation of tibet
tibet would not be
a temporary part of china right now had
it not been for mr nero and there are so
many other things that one can speak
about
there are entire books written about
this topic
so
so yeah that in brief is what mr nero
did
uh
he was in a way the architect of modern
india he ensured that india did not grow
rapidly
he imposed his version of fabian
socialism in mediocrity in india which
led to the nairobian rate of growth one
or two percent per year instead of i
mean when you have a newly uh liberated
country when you have a developing
economy it can easily
expand at the rate of 10 or more per
year for a couple of decades
but mr nehru choked and stifled all
development in india
which led to the nehru in great rate of
growth which led to incredible misery
and poverty all artificially created
so these are some of the
great achievements of mr nehru the the
one of the architects of modern india
india if today it is a third world
country it is
entirely or to a large part because of
the policies of mr nehru and of his
successors
who ran india for the best part of
five six seven decades
so these are some of the contributions
of mr nehru to india
good question
it's a good question
okay what else this is by tripty parab
tripty asks why do people relate hindu
gods with aliens
good question i think it is mostly done
in the west but now because of the
western influence in india even indians
are starting to believe that there may
be some
alien uh connection when it comes to
hindu gods
see when you watch the marvel movies you
have all this entire pantheon of nordic
gods you have thor you have odin you
have freyja and you have so many you
have what's his name uh
what's the name
uh
who is thor's brother half brother
the androgynous personality very
interesting character loki isn't it loki
and then you have the the wolves
fenrir and the other wolf and so many
more this is the entire nordic pantheon
of gods
uh
europe had a polytheistic culture before
it was stamped out by christianity about
a thousand or so years ago so
the marvel universe is all about the
nordic gods well the truth is that the
nordic gods are european interpretations
of the roman and greek gods
which in turn are roman and greek
interpretations
of the original indian vedic pantheon so
you have the thunder god indra who is
whose main weapon is the hammer and the
thunderbolt and you have an entire
pantheon of gods around him which are
which is represented in the greek
pantheon the roman pantheon the slavic
pantheon
the the
golish pantheon the celtic pantheon and
the nordic pantheon
now
these gods the ancient vedic gods they
are the original superheroes they had
all these powers
i mean
they they are they were supposed to have
all these supernatural
and superhuman powers
and
if you examine the kind of power of the
head it does sound not like mythology or
magic it sounds like science fiction
magic is
something that is completely fantastic
it has no grounding in logic or reality
but science fiction is something that is
hypothetically possible maybe in the
future maybe if you have advanced enough
technology
so if you look at the superhuman and
superhuman powers
superhero-like powers of the ancient
indian gods
it does sound like science fiction more
than magic or fantasy or mythology
and that's why people have speculated
especially in the west that maybe some
aliens visited india and in the the
poor indians they started worshiping
those aliens and god as gods and that's
how the ancient vedic pantheon of gods
was created there is a speculation that
has
been recurring it's a recurring theme or
motif in
in the west
and you have all these uh these
tv series like ancient aliens etc that
portray lord shiva as as an alien and
they portrayed the great mountain
kailash mount kailash as the center
which is considered to be the center of
the universe
as some place which has some hidden
uh alien technology within or something
like that and so on and so forth this is
just
blind speculation it has no basis or
foundation in reality
and they call themselves ancient alien
theorists or something i have seen a
couple of episodes very entertaining but
ridiculous
so that is the reason why people uh
because hindu gods
seem
and ancient
hindu epics etc they seem to have not
magic but very advanced technology
that's why many people in the west
especially try and relate hindu gods
with aliens and today that nonsense is
entering into india because indians
nowadays watch all these series which
are available everywhere on tv etc
and now these these thoughts and these
beliefs have permeated into the indian
consciousness to some extent
so that is the reason why they do it but
it has no basis in actual reality
shaibala says is stonyx i
a russian origin name or a pashtun
origin name because whenever someone
hears the word sanik zai
they compare that with the slavic or
russian name
so i don't think see the pashtun the
original pashtun language if you
if you decontaminate it of the turkic
and arabic in persian words it is
nothing but an in indo-aryan language or
at most an indo-iranian language
it's its grammar
and its
indigenous vocabulary is all rooted in
sanskrit
it is now filled it is now it it now is
replete with a lot of arabic and turkic
and persian words for sure
so it does sound in some way similar to
persian or even to to to
kashmiri in the dark languages etc
so if you look at the history of
afghanistan in the past 1000 years
there's a lot of foreign influence
because afghanistan was the
frontier outpost of india gandhara
and it was the first region to be
invaded occupied and converted by the
turks
and later on by various other influences
as well so there's a lot of turkic
influence there's a lot of there is a
certain amount of arabic influence and
there is a certain amount of persian
influence as well
in the pashto language and especially in
the names of the people in afghanistan
because today if you look at the names
of the people of afghanistan these are
all foreign names their ancestors did
not have names like these their
ancestors had sanskrit names
so everything has been turned around
converted and i think the word tanik zai
yusuf zai this zai that zai
it these are turkic origin
names
i think zai i'm i'm not don't hold me to
this
uh if i recall correctly zai means
descendant of or member of a tribe or
something like that
so stanix essentially means
i think it means member of the sonic
tribe or something like that so you have
sonic zai you have yusuf zai and various
other names which are all
influenced by the turkic languages such
as chagatai language and various other
languages some of which are extinct some
of which still persist in various parts
of central asia etc
so it is not a russian origin name it is
not an indi indo-iranian name it is not
a pashtun origin name i think it is
rooted in
one of the
turkic
languages
satoru gojo says what was the rivalry
between nicola tesla and thomas edison
does edison play a misunderstood figure
in history
uh i haven't studied this part of
history in great detail i know that
there was
a rivalry i believe that nikola tesla
the serbian inventor and scientist was
extraordinarily talented
but he was not good with it at
business and finance and that's why he
did not do well in life
i think he invented a great
number of very interesting uh
inventions
and i'm not sure if there was a rivalry
with thomas edison i there may have been
i am not entirely sure i think tesla
advocated the alternating current and
thomas edison was an advocate of direct
current
and clearly alternative alternating
current uh ac current voltages are far
superior to the direct voltage and so on
so i think there is an interesting story
to it but i am not entirely sure i'm i
have not studied this specific episode
of the history of science in any detail
it's something that i would like to
study in the future if i get the time
yes it's an interesting chapter of
history but you are right there was some
kind of rivalry and
clearly nikola tesla was a superior
scientist in in this case
okay some more questions some more
questions
abaisha says is it possible for a human
to live more than a thousand years and
do you believe in chiranjeevi like
ashotama
who are still alive
well as far as i understand the
uh
the human lifespan doesn't typically
exceed 100 years or so i think the
average lifespan in most of the
countries especially the developing
countries is close to some in the 70s
and 80s i think i think the japanese are
the longest lived people in the world
their average lifespan maybe in the
early 80s
if i am
approximately correct
and in the developing world the life
lifespans are still average life
expectancy is still less than that
so that is the averages of the world i
know that in the past in india and other
places especially in the east you have
people who have lived very long
lives
more than 100 sometimes in the 120s i
think there are people in japan who have
lived that sort of uh
who have reached that sort of age 110
120s i think the oldest known person
who lived the longest was in in his or
her 140s i think
so that's what we know from the data
that we have
and we know that there is a process of
aging
as you grow older there are there is a
certain biological process that
telomeres in in your chromosomes they
start
shortening et cetera and that seems to
contribute to the aging process in human
beings
and eventually the the
the aging reaches the level that
it is not possible to sustain life
beyond a certain
uh beyond a certain limit of time
so i from see as a scientist my
perspective is very clear the data says
that it is not possible to live a
thousand years it's not possible
typically to live more than 110 years or
so it's very rare for somebody to cross
100 years even today
so
from a purely scientific perspective
from a data driven perspective no it's
not possible there is no known instance
proven instance of a human who has lived
more than 140 or so years
so
i think it is not possible given the
evidence that we have
do i believe in chiranjeevi or immortals
immortals like ashothama well according
to science it's not possible for a
person to be immortal or to live more
than a thousand more than like i said
140 years
so from a factual data-driven
evidence-driven perspective it is not
possible
now obviously we know that
our understanding of science isn't
complete
our understanding of the of the universe
of nature etc of our own biology is very
fragmentary it's very rudimentary we
know almost next to nothing we don't
know about the brain we don't know about
the body we don't know about nature the
universe so it is possible that certain
things may
exist that
seem unlikely from the perspective of
the information that we currently have
so i am
i'm very skeptical
it is most likely it would not happen
but i would not rule it out a hundred
percent i have an open mind
i do understand as a scientist that
there are things that we still do not
understand
i don't know that i do
i do recognize the fact that there are
things that science still doesn't
understand it's not because science is
wrong it's because of our understanding
our knowledge is incomplete and
rudimentary science isn't wrong our
understanding of science
is incomplete
our instruments
are
maybe not precise enough our senses may
not sense everything
uh as as deeply as we would want them to
and so on
so i have an open mind i would not say
that i would not certainly not make fun
of anybody who believes in in in such
possibilities but from my perspective i
am extremely skeptical that anybody
would live more than 130 140 years
so that's my
perspective
right let me see some more questions
harsh kubar says why is the average
height of indians decreasing
you told that the people who invaded
europe were indians but indians do not
have that much height
well i am 6 1. i'm six one there are
many people in in india who are much
taller than me if you i mean uh do we
have any data that that demonstrates
that the average of the average height
of indians is decreasing because from
what i have seen the newer generations
of kids are all taller and taller each
each time you go to any school or
college you look at the kids the boys
and girls good god they're tall by the
time a boy or a girl is 12 13 14 years
old they're over five five and a half
feet
some of them reach six feet by the time
they are 15 or 16. i mean i think the
average height of indians is increasing
substantially
and yes i did say that the people who
invaded indians
invaded europe about 5000 years ago
where of indian origin the yamnaya
people now the word yamnaya
is not an indian word it's a russian
word the word yamna means a pit
in the ground in russian
and these people they buried their
deceased
persons in pit graves that's why the
russians called them the yamnaya people
it's not an indian word okay it's a
russian word so these people the yamnaya
invaders of europe who totally
transformed the genetics of europe
overnight almost they were of indian
origin they their predominant uh genetic
lineage petroleum lineal lineage was r1b
and as i have shown in the past the the
physical features etc appearance was all
indian they had light brown skin they
had dark hair dark eyes and they look
like indians these reconstructions have
been done it proves it beyond a doubt
the genetics are also indian r1b which
is
uh a descendant of the r1 lineage which
originated in india and so on so yes
they were indians and their average
height was approximately six feet
six feet tall there were horse riders
they were very active individuals they
were meat eaters
which means they did not follow the
vedic rituals after they left india they
became lectures because they stopped
following the vedic rituals
in their entirety so they were invaders
they were horse riders they were
warriors and there were meat eaters they
ate a lot of meat
and they drank a lot of milk and dairy
products if you live that sort of
lifestyle you gonna be muscular tall and
strong
it's all about lifestyle over a few over
a few generations
so yes they were of indians today
indians why are indians uh comparatively
comparatively short today why is it let
me explain why
over the past 300 years before today the
british systematically starved india
we had over a hundred million deaths
minimum
over a century and a half which were all
the results the consequence of
systematic deliberate artificially
engineered famines which the british
engineered when you don't have nutrition
you don't grow tall even after 1947
during the neheruvian regime and the
congress regimes india was still
starving because there was no growth in
india the economy had been stifled
by the socialist policies of this of
these regimes and that's why indians did
not have nutrition
look at the indian sports teams in the
past they were all short they were all
thin look at the indian sports teams
today
don't you see the difference
so that's the thing when you have
sufficient nutrition you automatically
grow to your fullest potential i think
that this entire
you know in in sports especially there
was this this uh
this truism that indians
are not
a martial people they are not good at
sports they are weak they are thin
indians don't bowl fast was what they
used to say in cricket today india has
the most
the deadliest fast bowling attack in the
world
so all this is myths it's nonsense look
at data look at statistics think clearly
think logically think analytically
indians
are not a short people what happened
what you see what you have seen in
recent times is the consequence of 300
years of of atrocious
colonization
and oppression and starvation
now that india is finally
no longer in the situation you are
seeing the average height of indians
increasing significantly so that's
the truth in fact
no i don't know what is the vedic rashmi
theory sorry i don't know what it is
never had the time to study that
who are the biharis
the biharis are the descendants of the
people of magadha
roughly that area i think you had magadh
which was in bihar its capital was
partly putra
right the ancient city of parliament
which is the modern city of patna which
is still the capital
of one of the major cities in india
so the bihari people
are the descendants of the great people
of magadha
that's what the bihari people are
and of course they are not a separate
race or a separate ethnicity they are
indians
we are all indians we may all look
different because we are genetically so
diverse and yet we are genetically very
much alike
so you have all kinds of
different expressions of genetics in
india you have shorter people you have
taller people you have people with
lighter skin people with darker skin
people with various
with a variety of
facial characteristics and phenotypes
and all that and yet we are one
ethnicity so the biharis are the
descendants of the great people of
maghad and they are very much an
integral
part
of the indian population
akshay asks did raja bhoja kill mahmoud
of ghazni no as far as i know
he did not do any such thing
uh
there is no evidence that he did so
according to the historical records etc
this such an event did not happen
of course as we know history is often
incorrect history is often full of lies
so maybe
maybe somebody may want to re-examine
this chapter of history but as far as i
know from the best evidence that we have
from
the historical consensus this did not
happen
all right
ranjana asks did magic exist in the era
of ramayana and mahabharata no magic
does not exist
there are things that may
feel or sound like magic but that is
always advanced technology a technology
that is sufficiently advanced advanced
is indistinguishable from magic
so when i switch on a light bulb
my cat or my dog would not understand
the technology they would not understand
how it works so they would think that we
are magicians
similarly
if some somebody is in possession of a
very advanced technology that i don't
understand or we all don't understand
that we then we may feel that it is
magic
but it is actually technology
so magic doesn't exist all that exists
is technology advanced technology now it
does look like from the depictions of
the
warfare in the ramayana and mahabharata
it does look like like i said
science fiction it does sound like
science fiction it sounds like you had
extremely destructive weapons that were
very well targeted etc that could be
targeted
uh
in a variety of ways with your thoughts
and so on so that sounds like science
fiction that doesn't sound like magic it
sounds like very advanced technology now
did such technology actually exist we
don't have any evidence of that today
but clearly the imagination at least did
exist
and the imagination was thousands of
years ahead of its time
and maybe the technology may even have
existed but we don't have any any any
proof of that as of today
so that is the answer magic did not
exist
please talk uh manika says please talk
about jesus in kashmir documentary is it
true well i haven't watched the the
documentary that you're referring to uh
i have never been
interested in the
in this specific uh story
of mr christ
of of jesus christ uh there is no
historical evidence that
mr jesus actually existed
uh it is all
mythology it's all myths there is no
hard evidence
in the historical record in the
archaeological record that jesus christ
actually existed
and therefore if we don't know whether
he existed or not what is the evidence
that he came to kashmir i mean what
evidence does anybody have
beyond tales beyond stories
isn't that what the historians called
mythology when it comes to india
that you people have these tall tales
and all but there is no evidence well
where's the evidence for mr jesus christ
and if there is no evidence for his
existence then what's the point of was
telling stories about him coming to
india
so that's my position on on this
particular matter
uh maybe
oh sorry i think my mic was muted so
what i'm saying is that maybe he did
exist
uh i am open to the possibility that
jesus christ may have existed
and if he existed maybe he
he went somewhere maybe he went to india
but what's the evidence do we have a
single piece of hard evidence in
controvertible evidence that proves this
no
so so that's all i have to say about
this it's not something that interests
me a lot
neeta says
jain people jain people j what's your
specific question nita do you have a
specific question
on gender well what about the jain
people the jain people are indian people
dharma is a is
very much part of
dharma
it is not a dharma which means it is
dharma well dharma is the eternal the
masanatan dharma and therefore jain
dharma
the jain perspective the jain philosophy
the jain
world view
is
a very important component of the larger
dharmic tradition
and
i haven't really studied the history of
jainism in
sufficient enough detail
we know that the
last great tirthankar vardaman mahavir
he was a
okay so
so vardhan mahavir was a contemporary it
is believed of
gautam buddha
roughly
and it is uh
according to the jaina tradition there
were many more
tirthankars before vardaman mahavir
and therefore it looks like uh from this
evidence from the from the
records of the of the of jainism it does
look like jainism is jaina dharma is
extraordinarily old maybe as old as the
overall dharma itself
so that's what i can say about it maybe
i shall study this in more detail in the
future and perhaps in the future i may
speak about this in a with in in more
depth
but
what i can say is that jain dharma is is
an extremely
significant and important component of
overall dharma and it is extremely old
maybe as old as the entire dharmic
tradition itself possibly perhaps
aryan chakravarthy says did ancient
indians eat meat this is a very
controversial topic no matter what
answer i give i'm gonna get some
negative comments so listen
according to the archaeological record
see we know that indians
we know that the indian subcontinent
has been inhabited for about 70 000
years
the first place which was
settled in a permanent manner
after the out of africa invasion of out
of africa migration of the homo sapiens
species the first place that was
permanently settled was the indian
subcontinent
this happened about 70 000 years before
today and indians have been living in
the indian subcontinent ever since the
oldest genetic lineages whether they are
patrilineal lineages or matriline
lineages they are both indian lineages
they both originated in the indian
subcontinent haplogroup f in term in
which is a patrilineal haplogroup
and haplogroups m and n which are
matrilineal haplogroups so india is the
original out of africa founders zone
right
and according to the archaeological
record we find evidence of fish hooks we
find evidence of harpoons you know
what's a harpoon it's a spear that you
throw at your
at whatever animal you're hunting we
find evidence of arrowheads and so on
so it is clear that there was hunting
activity in ancient india there was
fishing activities in ancient india
and we know that even during the time
of the mauryan dynasty
meat eating was
to some extent uh prevalent
we know that uh
the great gotham buddha
his it is it is most likely that his
last meal
was pork his last meal before he
uh attained nirvana before before he
died
so it is clear that indians did eat meat
now according to
dharma
violence is not a good thing ahinsa is
indeed the parma dharma
so
according to the dharmic scriptures
according to the dharmic worldview the
superior way of living is to not eat
meat the superior way of living is to be
a vegetarian and refrain from violence
even on helpless animals that is the
better the superior
way of living now everybody cannot live
this lifestyle if you are a warrior you
need more protein you need to be
stronger physically
and
therefore it is quite common for the
so-called martial races the chatrias the
rajputs the kings etc
the aristocracy especially the warriors
to eat meat so meat eating
is indeed
and has been historically prevalent
especially among
the warrior class in india
so ancient indians did eat meat i am not
saying i am not passing a value judgment
on whether it is a good thing or a bad
thing
i think
it is not nice it is not a good thing to
to
indulge in
the slaughter of helpless animals if it
is possible to refrain from eating meat
if it is possible to
to
uh eat sufficient protein without eating
meat then it is the better way of living
in my opinion it is definitely
the right thing to do
to be vegetarian or vegan or whatever
you call it i think vegetarianism the
indian way is the superior way in my
opinion which is what our
dharmic scriptures
prescribe as the superior way of living
but yes to answer your question in short
after all this
indians ancient indians to some extent
some of them definitely did eat meat
um
mohit says currently the muslim
brotherhood pakistan qatar turkey
are using propaganda against india assam
case
planning to ban indian goods should we
let that happen listen what other people
do is not in our control
what we can control is what we do
with our policies and our actions
if pakistan and qatar and turkey or
whoever it is i i'm not sure well i have
not read about
uh any such event that
they are planning to ban something
indian goods or something if they do
go ahead and ban something well how does
it affect us we are an enormous
and we have a global
market so if these small countries like
pakistan qatar
turkey etc
would want to ban trade with india well
go ahead enjoy
these are small economies they don't
really matter to us anyway we don't have
any trade any significant trade with
pakistan
and i don't know about turkey but who
cares
in case it is true i haven't heard any
such news i don't know what is the assam
case
but you know what
will it happen we have plenty of other
trading partners to to trade with it
doesn't matter
and it would be
i think it would be immature and stupid
for them to do such a thing actually
because it would expose the true
motives and agenda
okay let's take some more questions my
friends
certain questions i have already
answered listen guys i
it is impossible for me to
answer every question i would like to
answer every question but i will take
questions that i have not answered
before so in case you have a question
that i am not able to answer or i'm not
answering right now
i would request you to go to my channel
after this session is done or maybe
later
and search for your specific question
because i have answered hundreds of
questions by now i have put out all of
these not all but many of these answers
in the form of short clips so in case i
am not answering any of your questions
right now go to my channel search for
your question most likely it has been
answered and most likely it is already
there in the form of a short clip so
maybe you can look that up so in case i
don't answer your questions don't be
discouraged
i'm just one person but i have answered
hundreds of questions and these are all
there
many of them are still are already there
on my channel so you can look that up
now let's take some more questions
uh
aikichi onizuka
looks like sounds like an anime name
isn't it anime character is it okay uh
so the question is you said there are no
traces of chingaskhan being a tyrant but
it is said that he killed his brother or
brothers when he was young
you said the same for emperor ashok
please clarify
excellent question excellent
question thing is this
yes triggers khan did kill one of his
brothers whose name was bechter
so uh this is when he was a teenager
when he's when his family had been
exiled and uh expelled from their
ancestral tribes the bourgeois tribe
so when uh when timothy his his birth
name was temujin when temujin's father
died his father was the the chieftain of
this borjigin tribe when the emoji's
father died
there was
a coup of sorts
and one of his father's main warriors
took over the leadership instead of
temujin or one of his brothers which
should have been done because so it was
a coup of sorts and
the emergence family was expelled from
the tribe
and they were left to dr to die in the
mongolian wilderness
because in mongolia during the winters
the temperature can go down to minus 30
degrees or so it is almost impossible
for a family to survive without the
support system of a tribal group so they
were left to die but they managed to
survive now this half brother of the
emojin
bechter
was stealing the food that was supposed
to be shared among the entire family he
was hunting and instead of sharing it
with the family he was consuming it
himself on the side
and this was causing the family it would
have caused the family to die out of
starvation because all of the food was
being consumed by this one boy
bechter who was elder to temujin so
temujin and his brother kachyun i
believe they got together
they hunted this guy down and they
killed him it was
fratricide it was the killing of their
own brother
but the only option there were only two
options you either kill him or you all
starve and he survives
so i think that when
so it was it was a harsh rough and very
tough decision
but
when you are faced with the primal
realities of survive of survival
then maybe such a thing may be justified
maybe we
we live civilized lives
we
we don't ever
we are never put in a position when you
have where you have to take somebody's
life and i hope it never happens to any
of us
but those was those were different days
it was a different world it was a very
very harsh world
and i think he had to do what he had to
do
when you are rising
to the leadership of a country you have
to do hard things if you want to serve
your country and its people you have to
first fight
your way to the top
and fighting your way to the talk
doesn't top doesn't happen
with ahinsa and gandhian philosophy
it is a tough
harsh world it is survival of the
fittest
and only when you rise to the very top
can you actually serve your people so
you know morality you know armchair
moralizing i'm not saying your arms are
moralizing i am saying it is a tendency
for us who live in the 21st century
comfortable peaceful lives we have a
tendency to kind of moralize and pass
judgments on people of who lived in
other times
but the world is a very harsh place it
can again become very harsh overnight
so i think he had to do what he had to
do now when we compare him with ashok
there is a very big difference yes ashok
also killed his brother his half
brothers etc but after temujin killed
his brother and eventually when he
became the khan of the mongol people he
was a very scrupulously fair king
he was a very fair ruler he had a very
clear set of laws which which applied to
everybody irrespective of their position
in the society it was
a meritocracy it was 100 transparent and
fair
there was no persecution of people
of any kind
except for the enemies of the nation
now when it comes to ashok he was a
tyrant he oppressed his people he
indulged in persecution of certain
religious communities because they had
opposed his actions in killing his
brothers and his family members and so
on so he was a vindictive
tyrannical person ashok did that he
tyrannized his own people he oppressed
his own people
and he destroyed the kingdom of kalinga
and in indulged in horrific slaughter
which was not really justified so
chunguskhan
invaded other countries
only in retaliation
there was no
uh only when there were just causes for
war
now was there any just cause for war
between magda and kalinga was there any
just cause for ashok to go and invade
and destroy kalinga there was none and
yet he did that so there is a very
significant difference
between these two historical
personalities between chingus khan and
ashok
shingiskan was by far
the
fairer
and superior ruler in all ways in a
multiple in a multitude of ways compared
to ashok the tyrant
okay i can see some other questions that
i've already answered please look them
up if your question is not answered
today look it up on my channel most
likely you will find the answers
okay
this is a very good question
uh the question is you said that gandhi
was a british
stooge british agent etc but what
personal benefit did he get
why would a person forsake his family
and live the life of a beggar he could
have
spent a luxurious life under the british
listen everybody listen we are all
motivated by different things
some of us want wealth
some of us want fame
some of us want luxury some of us want
to live a life of leisure without any
work
some of us
are motivated by power
and so on everybody has different
motivations do not look at historical
figures from your perspective maybe
what motivates you is one thing but what
may be what motivates them is a
different thing people who rise to the
position of historical figures
are not regular normal people
their motivations are complex and often
ordinary people don't understand those
motivations
now yes gandhi mohandas gandhi spent
much of his political life wearing just
a single piece of cloth a loincloth he
looked like a beggar
yes
but do you understand the lifestyle he
led
he had an army of servants his assistant
and his entourage
when he traveled by trade he traveled in
a third class compartment but he was the
only traveler in that compartment the
entire compartment would be booked for
him
it would be a third class compartment
but he would travel like a king in that
third class compartment there would be
nobody else and there would be a couple
of other compartments that would also be
booked for mr gandhi and in those other
two compartments his assistants his
helpers and his
his entire entourage would travel with
him
sarojini naidu said
that it costs us a fortune
to keep mr gandhi in apparent poverty it
was not poverty
it was not poverty he traveled one man
in an entire compartment
so what if it's a third class
compartment you have to go beyond what
you see on a superficial level
mr gandhi
he did not live the life of a beggar he
had an army of people at his back and
call who would obey him instantaneously
without question
he had the entire machinery of the
congress party at his disposal night and
day at the moment's notice they will do
whatever he said
mohandas gandhi was motivated by a
number of factors
he was motivated by power power always
trumps wealth this is something i have
been saying since the beginning of this
channel power always trumps wealth you
may be enormously wealthy but a
politician can ruin your life in a
minute
jack ma was incredibly wealthy what
happened to jack ma in china
despite his enormous wealth
an ordinary
worker of the chinese communist party
has more power than jack ma and that has
that is something we have seen in the
past few months
if you look at the jack ma case
and so on so gandhi
did not need wealth he had an army of
servants and helpers and he had an
entire political system at his disposal
he was motivated by power
and he had other motivations he was a
lifelong
servant of the british crown
and he had certain other religious
motivations also which i will not speak
about today but
if you examine his own writings
then you will be able to discern what
his motivations were he was not a hindu
dharma guru he was the opposite of that
so this is just a little bit about mr
bohandas gandhi but you know what he did
spend a very luxurious life under the
british
and he served the british but he had
incredible
power in india he had the entire
machinery
of the british created congress party at
his disposal
so these are the benefits he got did he
forsake his family who said he forsook
his family
who says he forsook his family
please study gandhi's life in a little
bit of detail
he never gave up his family he never
gave up anything
he had all the material world at his
disposal
so
so i think it's a very good question
these are the things that indians don't
know because we simply study our history
textbooks and then we form a certain
mental image of these so-called leaders
and that's what we believe in throughout
our life the information the truth is
available in the public domain you don't
have to buy books
to study gandhi his own writings are
available for free online
study them
dig a little deeper into the life
and
the writings of mohandas gandhi in his
own words by his own hand
and then he will be able to uncover the
man behind the so-called mahatma
all right next question next question
um let's see some more questions
sushant verma says why have we found
remains of people from india but we
never bury someone as per the vedas i
think the indian dharmic tradition is
very complex it's very old
and they
see it's not a monolithic tradition
in the past
people buried their death their dead p
they did too
even today there are certain communities
who are hindu communities who buried
their dead
so it's not a monolithic culture it's a
very diverse culture
and i don't think there is anything in
the vedas against burying somebody
and you also have this practice of
samadhi right certain
very enlightened people sadhus etc
they choose to end their lives
in the samadhi state in which they
consciously and voluntarily
while meditating while sitting in the
padmasana or some position while
meditating they consciously decide to
end their lives by voluntarily
leaving their body
and such people are never cremated they
are buried we we have found
uh remains
uh skeletal remains of people
buried several thousand years ago in the
padmasana yogic position
sitting in the padmasana padmasan pose
so this is clearly a state of samadhi
so uh there is just one small
illustration of the way in which you
don't have a monolithic culture in india
uh so that is why we find we do find
remains of people who have been buried
you found the sonali burial too in which
which which was a
coffin burial a great warrior and a lady
as well and i think it's multiple
individuals who are found buried in that
manner so it's clear that you had
cremations you also had burials even in
the harappan
uh region
in the sapta sindhu region during the
harappan phase of our civilization you
find
burials you find symmetries but you also
find parts containing
burnt remains of human beings you know
so people who were cremated and their
ashes and whatever was left was buried
in pots so you have a
diversity a plurality of traditions
within
the ancient dharmic continuum so that's
why we find
many
examples of burials in ancient india
all right let's take some more questions
uh what are my thoughts about
demographic change in europe what will
be the future of europe after 50 years
explain deeply
yeah there seems to be a policy of uh
of so they call it
multiculturalism and cultural enrichment
or something whatever it is it's all
about
bringing in lots of immigrants into
europe
and uh
giving them permanent residency in
europe there are lots of people coming
in from from various parts of africa as
uh
as refugees and there are lots of people
coming in from
from from
the middle eastern regions
and europe many european countries most
european countries are pursuing this
policy of of bringing all these people
in and settling them in europe
so there is going to be demographic
change it's happening very fast in
europe the nordic country
the nordic countries even 10-15 years
ago had
very few
non-scandinavian people today you you
have a significant
foreign population there
so yeah it is it is a very rapid and
very significant demographic change i
think in france more than
10 15 percent of the people are of
non-french origin
and so on and so forth so yeah there is
this policy that is being pursued in
europe for whatever reason
of changing the demographics
and the culture
of europe to some extent
so i think after 50 years europe is
going to be a very different place it
will not feel like
what europe used to feel like maybe 10
20 years ago
i mean if you went to europe in the
1980s 1990s even in the 2000s
it was very different from what it is
even today and in the next 50 years i
think it's going to change
a lot
more
what is the purpose of doing all this
well i can only i can't even guess
but that's what's being done today
germany
france the united kingdom
all the eu nations etc poland for
instance is not allowing this to happen
they are against that they are holding
out they will not accept refugees or
migrants i think even the russians are
not doing that so
some countries
are not following this policy but the
majority of the eu nations
are doing it and what the purpose is
it's not clear to me
as of today maybe it is but maybe it's
not
all right let's take some more questions
type one civilization uh
chaitanya asks when do you think
humanity will become a type one
civilization it's most likely that
humanity may never become a type one
civilization uh see the kardashev scale
is all about exploiting your resources
exploiting your planet i don't think
it's even a good idea to exploit the
entirety of your planet and control all
its resources and everything that
happens
because that means that you have
enslaved
uh
all the non-human species and they are
nothing more than resources i don't
think that that's the way we should
we should
progress i think we are
but one species on this planet i think
all the species have the right to live
as equals
we are of course the predominating
species so we can do things but i don't
think it's a good idea to try and
control the climate in the environment
and everything
it may end up causing more more harm
than good because
we don't have anything near the
technology
and i don't know if humanity is going to
reach the stage where it will be able to
do it
and control everything on the planet
there is something called the great
filters
because you know there are
things that happen that prevent a
species from reaching that stage as you
know humans we humans are a very violent
very war like species even our closest
relatives the chimpanzees are very much
like us very violent
very brutal very war like it is in our
nature
to go to war
if you look at the history of humanity
in the past ten thousand years it's a
history of warfare
it's a history of conflict if you look
at the history of the past hundred years
it's a history of warfare and conflict
and if we are always
at war
and at conflict with each other
then how will we be able to cooperate
and build the technology that can
achieve a type 1 status for us because
to achieve that sort of
technology we would all have to
cooperate we cannot keep fighting and
competing with each other we have to
cooperate to reach that state and
therefore i it seems kind of unlikely to
me given our nature
our violent and
conflict
driven nature it seems unlikely that we
may
even reach their type one status so
i think
it's
unlikely i i personally think it's quite
unlikely that we will achieve it anytime
in the near future
all right some more questions
says why are history books still
spreading the colonial
mindset there are a number of factors
first of all the entire academic system
is mainly colonized
all our academicians
they don't do any original research i
mean less than one percent of india's
academicians teachers professors etc do
any actual research that benefits
society
they what they do is they simply teach
you textbook history whatever is written
in textbooks and these textbooks have
been
teaching the same nonsense since the 19
since the 19th century
and the system is such that it will not
allow anybody to express contrary
opinions
there are many
intelligent brilliant people in india
even in academia but the moment you try
to express a contrary opinion the moment
you try to do some research that goes
against the accepted narrative then when
you do that you are marginalized you are
you are prevented from publishing or
even if you publish the research you are
not allowed to rise to a prominent
position in academia and that's why the
entire academic system is
deeply
mentally colonized
i would say
they're a bunch of jokers that's all
they are unfortunately i was
i have been intimately connected with
academia my almost my whole life
so i am the right person to say this
that they are mostly a bunch of jokers
they are all mentally colonized they
they
and it is in their benefit to keep the
system the way it is because they owe
everything to the system and then you
have the
the larger system the known academic
system the bureaucracy of india the
governance system etc the politicians
they also benefit from the colonial
mindset because the moment indians
actually understand and be what's really
happening what's really happened and the
moment indians decolonize their mindset
the entire political system will crumble
the parties that have been exploiting
divisions
between indians
for decades
they will lose their political capital
they will fall out of power
for example the aryan dravidian theory
the divide which is a fake divide well
all the dravidian part is in southern
india
that is their staple political position
the moment this theory is proved wrong
which it is but the moment the textbooks
start teaching the fact that this is a
fake theory and when the students start
understanding this then they will no
longer vote for those parties which have
been spreading lies for decades
so that is the reason why the
politicians the bureaucrats the
academicians they are all in this
together they want to keep india
colonized because they benefit from it
that's the that's the sad truth
so that is why india's history textbooks
are still spreading the colonial mindset
they are still worshiping gandhi and
nehru they are still portraying india's
foreign invaders and occupiers as
india's saviors and they are portraying
indian india's indigenous culture as
primitive and backward and regressive
and patriarchal and misogynistic and
castest and what not
all
lies
so that's the reason why why
we have we are in this position right
now
neha asks what should i do apart from
learning sanskrit to become a good hindu
to be a good hindu you only have to be a
good person you don't even have to study
sanskrit
as long as you're a good person you will
be a good hinduise i would say
uh
what else could i recommend see the
thing you should do
is you need to
not you not only you neha but everybody
we what we need to do is we need to
learn our true history
we need to decolonize our mindset from
what our teachers our professors in our
textbooks are teaching us that we are
backward people our culture was backward
and and evil and all that
once we
understand that once we
acquire
a degree
of self-respect
then
we can be better hindus i would say and
of course one
to to be a hindu you would you would
need to know something about
uh our scriptures and all that and
that's why
you do need to
you can study scriptures etc
or ancient uh
vedas books etc
through english translations but very
often these english translations are
deliberately
uh they deliberately distort
some of these texts to make it look like
these texts are are misogynistic or
castes or or or regressive or
patriarchal or whatever you know that's
why the best thing to do is to learn
sanskrit and read the actual sunset
texts
otherwise you can read it in your mother
tongue whatever it is hindi or whatever
you know
that is a better option than than
studying it in english so there are a
number of things you can do
to become a better human being if you
become a better human being you will be
a better hindu
hinduism is about acceptance it's about
seeing everybody as equals
it's not about imposing a certain
worldview on people and saying that if
you don't
believe in my word viewer accept what i
said then you will go to hell so
hinduism is very different from the
abrahamic religions as long as you don't
live in abrahamic life you are you're a
good hindu so there's a number of things
that can be done
but i would say that learning sanskrit
will
build
is essentially the foundation to
studying the text of hinduism and to
build the self respect and understand
the richness of our culture
so that in brief
is some of the things you could do
okay let's take some more questions
uh harsh kumar says my friend thinks
that religion is the root cause of every
wrong thing happening
how should i convince him you know harsh
your friend is right
religion is the root cause of everything
that has gone wrong in the world in the
past 1000 years religion
religion is bad
dharma is not religion
there are three religions
those are the abrahamic religions a
religion is something that has one
prophet one god and one book
the definition of a religion is a system
that has one book
one god and one prophet it accepts
nothing else
it says that our way is the only way
everything else is is wrong everybody
else is an infidel who need to either be
killed or they need or they will go to
hell and burn in hell that is religion
so religion is the root cause of
everything bad that's happening in the
world or which has happened wrong which
has gone wrong in the world in the past
1 000 or so years
dharma is not religion
religions are the opposite the
antithesis of dharma
so you have the dharmic tradition which
incorporates
what we call hinduism and buddhism and
jainism and sikhism
but it also incorporates many animistic
beliefs
uh the mongolian version of dharma is
also very much valid with the swayambhu
symbol and all that
then you have the indonesian versions of
dharma which existed in the past you
have the
vietnamese champa version of dharma
which was dharma with champa
characteristics you have the shinto
dharma in in japan
which is
an animistic
tradition which has syncretized very
well with both the dharma
so all of this is not religion it is
dharma
dharma is the antithesis of religion
religion is the antithesis of dharma it
is these exclusivist supremacist
religions
the abrahamic religions that are the
root cause of everything that's going
wrong in the world it is what led to the
colonization of most of the non-european
world the americas
africa asia india especially all the
horrors of colonization
all the genocides they are caused they
were caused by these religions so yes
your friend is correct religion is the
root cause of everything wrong
but dharma is not religion
dharma is the right way to go it is the
way to go
okay some more questions
fourth dimension says don't you think we
got behind due to our lack of technology
progress you know what india was the
most technological advanced civilization
in the known universe in the
in the old days
look at the harappan era archaeological
record
we had the most advanced
hydroengineering
architecture and all that
way more advanced than any other ancient
civilization way more advanced than uh
mesopotamia babylon egypt and all that
yeah we did not build those enormous
pyramids because we did not have that
sort of mindset of enslaving people and
making them do such work but we had the
most superior technology it is not only
about technology it's also about
leadership
the reason we got we
we fell behind was because of the
prithviraj johan syndrome
we forgot what our great teacher acharya
vishnu gupta chanakya taught us
and we started treating barbarians and
brutal people with compassion and we
started treating them as equals
we started tolerating a dharma and
that's why we fell behind it had nothing
to do with technology
you may have the most advanced weaponry
but if you think your enemy is your
friend you are doomed
and when you have your enemy at your
mercy but you let him go then no matter
how much technology you have it's going
to be of no use to you that is the
reason for india's decline and today
india is still behind because we worship
people like mohandas gandhi
that defeatist person
who
imbued infused our minds with this
defeatist
attitude
that you should just
be passive
be non-reactive
don't try to progress
don't industrialize
stay
poor
your only livelihood should be from
weaving khadi just enough to put a few
morsels of food in your mouth that
mindset is
the enemy of progress
so it is these
wrong mindsets these harmful
mindsets and these harmful people these
enemies of our civilization who have
caused us to go behind it has nothing to
do with technology even today we have
nuclear weapons we have delivery systems
we have everything
and still we are a soft state
until 10 years ago we would not even
retaliate
to pakistani atrocities like the 2008
mumbai attacks or the 2006 mumbai
bombings or so many other terrorist
attacks in india despite having nuclear
weapons despite having the delivery
systems despite having an overwhelmingly
powerful military we were not reacting
it has nothing to do with technology it
has all to do with your mindset and the
kind of leaders you have
so that is the reason why india
was enslaved for a thousand years that
is the root cause of india's 1000 years
of humiliation
and it is something that should never
happen again it will not happen if you
all my friends learn this and understand
this that's the reason why i've been
talking for all these episodes
okay let's take some more questions
i'll do another 10 15 minutes all right
okay
what's my prediction about the expansion
of israel capturing jordan lebanon iraq
etc i do not see any such thing
happening
uh i do not see the middle east going to
war again
in the in the foreseeable future in the
near future i think israel is now
beginning to
uh
beginning to invest in friendly
relations with the
with various middle eastern countries
you had the abraham accords
that
took place during uh
president trump's uh presidency
so uh
i think the uae now has an official
embassy in israel the israelis also have
an embassy there i think
even the saudis
may be on the verge of
of establishing diplomatic relations
with israel
and so on so i think israel is now
trying to invest in good friendly
relationships with its middle eastern
islamic neighbors
i don't think why it should be
why it should not happen it is quite
likely that if you uh play the
diplomatic game properly and if you
assure your your neighbors that you
don't have any ill feelings or any any
ambitions of of destroying them then i
don't think i don't see why they cannot
have good relations so i do not see any
uh any desire
in israel for expanding further and
capturing the territories of jordan
labor and iraq etc yes there are
territorial disputes there are all these
grey areas and all
but i do not see an expansionist
tendency from israel in the near future
amrit says is the ever grand crisis
going to destroy china's economy well
evergrand is one of the major companies
i think it's a
real estate company is it or something
like that
so yeah it's going through a crisis
there is a lot
about china that is quite opaque china
is not a transparent economy it's not a
transparent nation there is so much
happening behind the scenes that the
chinese communist party is hiding from
the world
it is quite likely that the economic
miracle in china has ground to a halt
the past few years china has not been
growing at 10 plus it's been growing
officially at around 6 percent
and actually
in reality the growth may be maybe
even less than 2 percent
so the economic machine has most likely
ground to a halt and there are a lot of
problems in the chinese economy today
structural fundamental flaws in the
economy that could possibly
lead to
major problems in china
so the ever grant crisis may just be one
of these symptoms of
a much deeper
disease that afflicts the chinese
economy
it looks like china is going through a
number of crises there is a power crisis
in china right now many parts of china
are without power there is a lack of
coal and
and so much more
so it looks like the chinese miracle is
now slowing down significantly
and that could cause
problems
worldwide
especially in the asia-pacific region
especially
in china's neighborhood
it could uh cause some panic in china
and they may
they may perhaps indulge in some
military misadventures
to divert the attention of the people
that is a possibility and so on so it's
it's a time for all of us to be vigilant
to wait and watch and be very careful
about
what china is doing
especially in the in the coming few
years
uh crocs asks is a startup like spacex
possible in india
i think there is nothing that's
impossible in india all that needs to
happen is the government needs to get
out of the way right now it's impossible
in the current economic climate in the
the kind of regulations and bureaucracy
that you have it's almost impossible to
start a profitable
startup in india
there are so many problems that one does
not speak about
the moment you become profitable there
are these additional
taxes that are imposed upon you by the
local
powers politicians bureaucracy etc and
so on so it's almost impossible
as of today
to have a profitable startup in india
it's almost impossible
so i think what needs to happen in india
is reforms
we need to cr we need to crack down on
corruption
corruption is the biggest
hidden
problem in india
the and almost the entire
indian
governance system
to some extent or the other i am not
saying everyone is corrupt
there are definitely people with a great
amount of integrity in india's
bureaucracy in india's political system
in india's governance system but a
significant
percentage a significant portion of this
system is rotten
and corruption
is what is holding india's economy and
india's growth
down
if corruption is eradicated everything
is possible in india so i would say that
that's what needs to happen india needs
to
one of these days start a war on
corruption
it's going to be hard it's going to be
painful but that is the last step
in unleashing india's full potential so
that's what needs to happen so yes if we
can do that if the government can
take up this this big project of
destroying corruption in india then
anything is possible in india you can
have 10 startups like spacex in this
country there are so many brilliant
talented engineers and scientists people
who are passionate about
uh rocket science and aeronautics and
all that
it
i don't see
any shortage of talented people
engineers and scientists in india it's
all about
creating the right environment where a
startup can actually become profitable
and where you have the
the uh right kind of ecosystem
where you can get angel investment
funding and all that
today even if you have a great idea and
you are good at business it's very hard
to get funding
it's very hard to to get the kind of
funding that you need so all these
things need to happen the right kind of
system needs to be put in place the kind
of system that was once there in silicon
valley in california so if we can do
that if the government can
take this up then anything is possible
india is a land of incredible immense
untapped potential
that's what we need to unleash
all right some more questions some more
questions
uh
should hindus eat non-veg it's your
personal choice there is no compulsion
in hinduism
uh it's it's your personal choice i
would say that eating
i would say that being a vegetarian is
the superior way of life
it is what our sastras and our
our teachings say
that it is
better it is it is a superior way of
life if you do not indulge in
the eating of meat or in in the
slaughter of helpless animals so that is
a better way of living
but
you know it's it it's also been a part
of hinduism so it's your choice personal
choice what you want to do
there is no right or wrong the it is to
some extent wrong but
it is not an enormous sin or it is not
something that is taboo
in indian culture in hinduism so
at the end of the day it's an individual
choice
this is an interesting question is there
even a slight chance of indian north
sentinel island people
knowing the indus valley script or is
there no linguistics
um these people are the last
possible uncontacted tribe on our planet
um
they are completely isolated we don't
know what language they speak i'm sure
they have some language that must be a
very old language very ancient language
uh we don't know what language they
speak nobody has studied that i don't
think they have any script in a written
script or anything
so most likely i would say 99.99
i don't think there is any connection
between them and the indus valley script
or language i don't think there was any
contact between these people's ancestors
and our ancestors from the harappan era
of our civilization so most likely
there was no such connection
paramjit says hello from stockholm hello
pramjeet do you think that pakistan was
hiding bin laden
yes
pakistan was hiding bin laden we know he
they were like they were hiding him this
the compound in which he was
living for many years when he was hiding
for many years was right next to the
pakistani military academy
in abbottabad
so it's clear that they kept him where
they could observe him and monitor him
at all times
so yes
it is well known now by now that
pakistan was actively the pakistani
military and isi were actively hiding
bin laden they were very much aware
of his
presence right next to their
military academy so yes pakistan was
indeed hiding osama bin laden
is eating beef acceptable in hinduism no
it is not acceptable in hinduism if you
eat beef you're not a hindu
of course there are people who do
practice hinduism
who do uh
eat beef as well
so that is the the conundrum that is the
thing about modernity about india being
so deeply mentally colonized that these
practices have now cracked into india
there are people who are hindu by name
and who may even practice some forms of
hinduism some rituals from traditions
and yet who do eat beef and they feel
there's nothing wrong with it
but according to hindu tradition eating
beef is
a great sin so yeah i would say that it
is not acceptable in hinduism
tushar says monarchy or democracy
well there is no right
system there is no wrong system
[Music]
india is a democracy today a western
style democracy with the british style
westminster system
parliamentary system and all that right
that's what we have today
now
think back to the last time when india
was a great culture a great civilization
what was the system then
was it a western-style democracy or was
it a monarchy
if you look back at india's history the
times when india has been at its
greatest
when india has been the greatest
civilization was when we had emperors
and monarchs
that is an undeniable fact
but it is also true at the same time
that india is the mother of democracy
democracy is not a greek invention it is
something that emerged out of ancient
india
we had a hybrid system we would have a
king or an emperor or a queen
but that individual
was duty-bound
to listen to the people and to obey the
people's wishes
their highest morality
for the king was the long-term
prosperity of the kingdom and the people
and they would have an advisory council
who would advise them and
who could override a decision of the
king or the emperor that was also there
so india had
a hybrid system we had kings and
emperors and queens but we also had
democracy
at the local
levels you know and all that so
there is no right system or wrong system
whatever works best for your country is
the right system every country is
different every culture every
civilization is different india is the
oldest civilization that we know of
it is the oldest continuously existing
civilization so i would say that we need
to re-examine the way we are
governing the country the kind of system
we have accepted it is an inferior
system this western system
i would say it would be much better if
we were to
examine our history and draw inspiration
from that the era in which we were the
greatest and the most prosperous and
most successful civilization and most
advanced civilization of all time
what was the system of governance then
we should try and replicate that i am i
am not against that
i have nothing against any specific
system but what the bottom line is that
the country and the people must prosper
that is the bottom line
so it doesn't matter what system you use
it doesn't matter whether the cat is
black or white as long as it catches
mice
so
monarchy
if it works who cares let it work
or even if you can make democracy work
great or maybe you can have a hybrid
system like we always said in the past
so it's all about that it's all about
the national interest and the prosperity
of the country and the people that's all
it is
that's the only thing that matters
lalala
all right lalala back to you sir
uh is putin's iron fisted rule keeping
russia together or is it destroying
russia well i don't see any signs of the
destruction of russia russia was on the
brink of destruction during boris
yeltsin's rule
the guy was a weak ruler when you have a
country as large as russia you need a
strong ruler you need a strong leader
boris yeltsin was
he was essentially a western puppet
and
russia survived because vladimir putin
came to power
it is his iron fisted rule that is
keeping russia together
if you have a weak leader then a country
as large as russia is bound to fragment
and disintegrate
the larger the country the stronger the
leaders you need
so it is putin's iron fisted rule that
is keeping russia together the only
question is what sort of succession plan
does he have because he will not
live forever he will not rule forever
so what kind of succession plan does he
have in mind i hope he's planning
something he's creating some system of
succession
that will continue his legacy forward
otherwise after he is done
then if a weak ruler comes
to power in his position then again
russia may go down
the same way as it did during maurice
yeltsin's time
okay miwan srivastava if the aryan
migration theory is false then how is it
possible
for the oldest swastika to be found in
eastern europe which dates thousands of
years before the oldest one in india
this one is a fact you are right sir
this is a fact the oldest known
swastika-like carving is something that
was found in ukraine it's about 11 000
years old
so
what does it say
does it prove that the rn migration
theory is false
or is it does it prove that it's true
that does it mean that there was an
aryan invasion of india
it proves nothing
there has been absolutely no archaeology
done in india
99.9 of india's archaeological truth is
still buried underground
so if you don't do any archaeology in
india and you found some and you find
something else where then you cannot say
that it means everything came from
outside
this is a logical inconsistency it's a
logical flaw there is no logic to this
claim
you find swastikas in africa you find
swastikas in southern america in
northern america you find swastikas
throughout the inhabited
world
and swastikas have been found in every
continent
i think ex with the exception of
australia they have been found
everywhere
and all of these are several thousand
years old
so it is more likely that the swastika
is something that emerged as a symbol of
auspiciousness
across the world
i am not making the claim that it came
from india i have never made the claim
but it's only in india today that that
that tradition still continues
so there is no real connection between
the swastika and the aryan invasion
migration theory
to try and connect those two is a
terrific
logical
uh
flaw
right it's it's a it's a leap of logic
that is not logical at all
okay let us take one more question one
more question
okay you said that women and
transgenders were treated equally in
ancient bharat but in the mahabharat
bhisma refused to attack shikhandi
saying it is shatriya dharma not to
attack women yes absolutely
it is part of indian culture to not
ever attack women women are never to
be subjected to violence
do you mean that there is in inequality
if you treat women with higher respect
than men
i don't see the logic here
women and transgenders and all whatever
it was they were all
treated with respect and the way of
showing respect to women who are
physically weaker than men is to never
ever attack a woman physically
that is the way you show respect it is a
biological fact
that women that females are much weaker
physically than men
they lack the hormone that makes men
strong testosterone
and therefore women are physically
weaker than the males
and therefore if you want to respect
women
you must never ever physically attack
them no matter what the situation
that is the way of showing respect it's
not about treating equally it's about
showing people adequate in proper
respect equality is nonsense there is no
equality equality is a mirage it's it's
a myth
i have never said everybody was treated
equally
i said everybody got the respect that
that everybody deserves
so if you if if a gender is weaker you
have to treat them differently
than the stronger gender
women typically do not fight in wars
it is only as a last resort that women
have had to fight in wars in india
as warriors but typically women have
never been part of the armed forces
today the indian supreme court is saying
that women should be part of the armed
forces that is stupid
don't we have 1.3 million people in
india half of which are males why do we
need women in the armed forces why
it is known that women are physically
weaker than men why do we need to force
women even if they feel that they are
strong and all why i mean it doesn't
make sense
your
soldiers your armed forces
should be the strongest fittest possible
individuals you can find and on average
the average male is stronger than the
strongest woman so this doesn't make
sense so my point is that
everybody was not treated equally some
people were treated with more respect
women were treated with more respect
than men
so bhishma refused to attack shukandi
because shikhandi was
not a male and that was the appropriate
thing to do
i don't see why it is a problem
i do not see why it is a problem at all
indian culture is not western liberal
voc nonsense
indian culture is superior and this is
the way it was done in india
and that is the reason why bheisma
refused to attack shikhandi because it
is against dharma to attack a non-male
person a person who is weaker than you
that is the way of dharma
and that's the answer
i
i hope it makes sense
all right all right all right let's take
one more question
or maybe a couple of more questions meat
says please tell us about underwater
cities found near the gulf of khambhat
many years ago
which is said to be from at least 7500
bce and why is there no serious research
done till today like i have said just a
couple of minutes ago there is no
archaeology being done in india no
serious archaeology
we know that there are underwater cities
in the gulf of khambhat we have found
the city of dwarka
off the coast
of the shore of present-day modern
dwarka exactly where the mahabharata
said it would be found
and one of the pieces of wood that was
carbon dated from that sunken city is
more than eight thousand
or nine thousand years old
so it and and it is known that it is not
that that ancient dwarka is not the only
sankan city in this region there are
many
man-made structures
under the sea in the gulf of khambhat
and i'm sure all across the coastline of
india and yet nobody is researching this
the asi is not
taking the initiative
to go and investigate this because they
have their own agenda which is of
glorifying the mughals and the british
and of restoring the mughal monuments
and british monuments
it's all about the bureaucracy and what
their agenda is the asi is a
bureaucratic organization
they are not professional archaeologists
they are bureaucrats there are some
among them a few or very few who are
actually good people like uh
sr rao
and dr bibi lal et cetera who are really
great archaeologists
but the majority of them are mentally
colonized fools
they are responsible for the wholesale
for overseeing and doing nothing about
the wholesale theft of indian
antiquities from temples and
archaeological sites and all so that is
the reason why they are not doing
anything
it will take some action from the
government from the central government
to
wake the asia up i would say that the
asi archaeological survey of india
needs to be disbanded
and a new professional body needs to be
created in its place
with proper funding
only then will seriously research ever
begin in india and only then will we be
able to uncover the truth about our
ancient past
okay okay i think that's enough for
today i have taken a number of questions
it's almost 1 hour 40 minutes so guys
thank you very much for all your
questions
thank you for your viewership i am
always and forever grateful that you all
choose to come
and watch
and participate in these live sessions
i'm very grateful thank you so much
thank you to all of you who have become
members so thank you to all of you who
have contributed thank you for all your
support all your
comments all your messages of support i
am very very grateful
so i am going to end this now uh we will
have another session just like this
tomorrow same time 9 p.m india
so i will see you then and i will take
more questions at that time
thank you very much to all of you have a
good day have a good night
bye see you tomorrow